<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jury-man charged, or, A letter to a citizen of London wherein is shewed the true meaning of the statute entituled, An act to prevent and suppress seditious conventicles ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12494397</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12494397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62463</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 210:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jury-man charged, or, A letter to a citizen of London wherein is shewed the true meaning of the statute entituled, An act to prevent and suppress seditious conventicles ...</title>
                  <author>H. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: H.E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Assembly, Right of.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62463:1"/>
            <p>The Jury-man charged; OR, A LETTER To a CITIZEN of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherein is ſhewed the true meaning of the Statute, Entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles.</hi> As alſo, the falſe Gloſſes and Interpretations detected. And it is evinced by Undeniable Reaſons that the <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are ordinarily committed to Priſon, by Juſtices of the Peace and Chief Magiſtrates of Corporations, upon that Statute, are not guilty of the breach of it; and yet in reaſon it is impoſſible to convict any man among us of <hi>being preſent at a Meeting, under pretence and colour of any exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in other manner than is allowed by the</hi> Lyturgy <hi>or Practice of the Church of England,</hi> except thoſe that in then Meetings are manifeſtly Seditious or otherwiſe notoriouſly wicked. And that that Juryman that finds any other perſon guilty, is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf guilty of Perjury, and liable to the Vengeance of God upon his Family and Trade, Body and Soul, in this world and that to come.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hales</hi> of Schiſm.</bibl>
               <p>For indeed all Pious Aſſemblies in times of Perſecution and Corruptions, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever practiſed, are indeed, or rather alone, the Lawful Congregations and Publick Aſſemblies; though according to form of Law, are indeed nothing elſe but Riots and Conventicles, if they be ſtained with Corruption and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:62463:2"/>
            <head>The JURY-MAN Charged: OR, <hi>A LETTER to a Citizen of</hi> LONDON, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS it is the nature of true Love and Friendſhip, both to wiſh and endeavour the Good and VVeal of thoſe we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in our hearts for Friends; ſo it cannot be but that the happineſs of the one will redound to the other, and there will need nothing to the making your Friend partner in your Joyes but the knowledge of them. But among all Goods that can beautifie a F<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd, none is comparable to that of a mind habituated to Holineſs, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> delighting to do the VVill of God. And becauſe God ſpeaks to us by our Conſciences, it muſt needs be our neceſſary duty to walk according to the Light we find in that Divine Cloſet. And inaſmuch as the Light and Knowledge, at leaſt a great part of it, comes from without, through the windows of our ſenſes, we ought by all means to keep thoſe <hi>Mediums</hi> pure and untinctured; for otherwiſe the Light in our Souls wil not be clear &amp; orient. How can I then but greatly rejoyce in you, whom I find not only willing to obey, but dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to know your Heavenly Maſters Wil? the former of theſe Divine Qualities ſeparates you from the multitude of the world that lies in wickedneſs and diſobedience, the latter diſtinguiſhes you from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Zealots and blindly obedient. Not but that I confidently believe that God that gave his Son for us when we were Enemies, will much more pardon and ſave us, being weak, and in ſome things ignorant Friends: but many and lamentable are the ſad Conſequences even of pardonable Ignorance, much more of the damnable Ignorance of thoſe that in killing and caſting out the Servants of God, <hi>think they do God good Service.</hi> And I have no ſlender grounds of fear leſt this may be the caſe of many of thoſe that are forward in executing penal Statutes upon Religious perſons for matters relating properly to their Religion and Conſcience. And leſt you may in the leaſt offend, through ignorance of any ſort, you are pleaſed to ask my advice what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62463:3"/>
you ſhould do, if it ſhould be your lot to be called forth on a Grand Inqueſt or other Jury, for the putting in execution the late Act enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles.</hi> I could wiſh you had made uſe of ſome other in this Queſtion, that had been well-skilled in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> rather than of me that am whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant in that ſtudy; but however, being aſſured you will pardon what you know flows from a ſincere intention, I ſhall not be afraid to give you my private judgment as a Chriſtian (whatever it is) in a caſe that may be my own as well as yours, though likely to be yours firſt. We have ſeen the Title of the Act already, it proceeds thus: —<hi>For providing therefore of further and more ſpeedy remedies againſt the growing and dangerous practices of Seditious Sectaries and other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal perſons, who under pretence of tender Conſciences, do at their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings contrive Inſurrections, as late experience hath ſhewed: Be it enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, by and with the advice and conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Common in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That if any perſon of the age of ſixteen years or upwards, being a Subject of this Realm, at any time after the firſt day of</hi> July, <hi>which ſhall be in the year of our Lord</hi> 1664, <hi>ſhall be preſent at any Aſſembly, Conventicle or Meeting, under colour or pretence of any exerciſe of Religion, in other manner than is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the</hi> Lyturgy <hi>or Practice of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in any place within the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>or Town of</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick <hi>upon</hi> Tweed, <hi>at which Conventicle, Meeting or Aſſembly there ſhall be five perſons or more aſſembled together, over and above thoſe of the ſame houſhold; Then it ſhall and may be lawful to and for any two Juſtices of the Peace, of the County, Limit, Diviſion, or Liberty wherein the Offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſhall be committed, or for the Chief Magiſtrate of the place where ſuch Offence aforeſaid ſhall be committed (if it be within a Corporation where there are not two Juſtices of the Peace) And they are hereby requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and enjoyned, upon proof to them or him, respectively, made of ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, either by Confeſſion of the Party, or Oath of Witneſs, or notorious Evidence of the Fact (which Oath the ſaid Juſtices of the Peace and Chief Magiſtrate respectively are hereby impowred and required to adminiſter) to make Record of every ſuch Offence and Offences under their Hands and Seals reſpectively; which Record ſo made at aforeſaid, ſhall to all intents and purpoſes be in Law taken and adjudged to be a full and perfect Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of every ſuch Offender for ſuch Offence: And thereupon the ſaid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62463:3"/>
Juſtices and Chief Magiſtrate respectively, ſhall commit every ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo convicted as aforeſaid, to the Goal or Houſe of Correction, there to remain without Bail or Main prize for any time not exceeding the ſpace of three months, Unleſs ſuch, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, give me leave to tell you, that there are ſome that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt the whole Act as null and void in it ſelf, as all Statutes are that are made againſt Piety, as this ſeems to them to be: but then they that thus judge, take it for granted that it forbids ſome exerciſe of Religion which God commands or allows, and in that caſe all Lawyers will readily confeſs it to be of no more force than King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> his Decree, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. againſt asking any Petition of God or man for <hi>thirty dayes</hi> ſave of himſelf, and which Decree <hi>Daniel</hi> was by a miracle defended in diſobeying.</p>
            <p>Another Exception which they conceive deſtroyes the whole <hi>Act</hi> is, its contrariety to the <hi>Fundamental Laws of the Land</hi> in reſpect of its proceedings; for it ſeems contrary to the beſt Clauſe in all that ſo much magnified <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> viz. <hi>chap.</hi> 29. <hi>Nullus liber homo capiatur vel impriſonetur, aut diſſeiſietur de libero Tenemento ſuo, vel liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus, vel liberis conſuitudinibus ſuis, aut ut legetur, aut exubetur aut aliquo modo deſtruatur, ver ſuper eum ibimus nec ſuper eum mittemus, niſi per legale Judicium parium ſuorum, vel per legem terra. Nulli ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, nulli negabimus aut differemus juſtitiam vel rectum.</hi> 
               <q>No Free Man may be taken, or impriſoned, or diſſeiſed of his free Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or his Liberties or free Cuſtomes, or Out-lawed or Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or any way Deſtroyed: Neither will we go upon him, or ſend upon him, but by lawful Judgment of his Equals, or by the Law of the Land. We will ſell to none, we will deny to none, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Juſtice or Right.</q> It is to be obſerved that that great <hi>Lawyer</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> 2d Part <hi>Inſt. p.</hi> 49. obſerves upon the Expoſition of <hi>Per Legale Judicium,</hi> that the manner of Trial by <hi>Juries</hi> was by Law before this Statute it ſelf, and ſo is more ancient than <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> And upon theſe words, <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>Niſi per Legem terra, But by the Law of the Land,</hi> he ſaith it is, <hi>without due Proceſs of Law</hi>; and that is <hi>by Indictment or Preſentment of good and lawful men where ſuch deeds be done, in due manner, or by Writ original of the Common Law.</hi> 
               <q>Againſt this Ancient and Fundamental Law, I find (ſaith he) an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> made, that aſwel Juſtices of <hi>Aſſizes,</hi> as Juſtices of the <hi>Peace</hi> (without any finding or preſentment by the <hi>Verdict</hi> of 12.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62463:4"/>
men) upon a bare Information for the King before them made, ſhould have full Power and Authority by their diſcretions to hear and determine all Offences and Contempts committed or done by any perſon or perſons againſt the Form, Ordinance, and Effect of any Statute made and not repealed, &amp;c. By colour of which <hi>Act</hi> ſhaking this Fundamental Law, it is not credible what horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Oppreſſions, and Exactions, to the undoing of infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of People, were committed by Sir <hi>Richard Empſon</hi> Kt. and <hi>Edmund Dudley,</hi> being Juſtices of the <hi>Peace,</hi> throughout <hi>England</hi>: And upon this unjuſt and injurious <hi>Act</hi> (as commonly in like caſes it falleth out) a new Office was erected, and they made Maſters of the Kings Forfeitures.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But at the <hi>Parliament</hi> holden in the firſt year of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, this <hi>Act</hi> of the 11th of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, is receited, made void, and repealed; and the Reaſon thereof is yeelded, for that by force of the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> it was manifeſtly known, that many ſiniſter, craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, feigned, and forged Informations had been purſued againſt divers of the Kings Subjects, to their great damage and wrongful vexation. And the ill ſucceſs hereof, and the fearful end of theſe two Oppreſſors, ſhould deter others from committing the like; and ſhould admoniſh <hi>Parliaments,</hi> That inſtead of this ordinary, and pretious Trial, <hi>Per Legem Terra,</hi> they being not in abſolute and partial Trials by diſcretion.</q> Thus far <hi>Cook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, Inaſmuch as this <hi>Act</hi> allows two Juſtices of Peace, or the chief Magiſtrate of the place, not only to be Witneſſes, but to paſs Sentence of Impriſonment or Fine, and make Record of the Offence, without any Finding or Preſentment by the Judgment of twelve men; it being contrary, both to the Cuſtome of <hi>England, Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, they judge it abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>nul</hi> and of <hi>no effect</hi>: So that thoſe that carry on the execution of it are liable to the ſame miſerable end with <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> aforeſaid. Beſides, That this Judgment and Record of one or two Juſtices of the Peace, is full two parts of the proceedings, whereby 5000. of his poor Neighbours may be Baniſhed from their native Country, their dear Wives, ſweet Babes, loving Friends, and all other accommodations, into another world, for <hi>ſeven years</hi>; yea, and if they return before that time expired, <hi>to be hanged as Felons</hi>: And all this for nothing but worſhipping God according to what they are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62463:4"/>
fully perſwaded to be his will. Is this according to the ſo much Celebrated Laws of <hi>England?</hi> Judge, O ye <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe we that this <hi>Act</hi> were as juſt in every reſpect as Juſtice it ſelf, and moſt necceſſary to the Weal of the Nation, ſo that at leaſt, a third part of the People would be deſtroyed without it be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed (as they are likely to be by the execution of it) yet it muſt by no means be executed upon thoſe that are not proved to be guilty of the breach of it: Let us ſee then, what is necceſſary to be proved againſt every man or woman that is juſtly convicted of Breach of this <hi>Act. Firſt,</hi> This Priſoner muſt be <hi>ſixteen years of age.</hi> 2ly, He muſt be <hi>a Subject of this Realm.</hi> 3dly. Ae muſt be <hi>preſent at an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, Conventicle or Meeting.</hi> 4thly. Such Aſſembly, Conventicle or <hi>Meeting</hi> muſt be held <hi>under colour or pretence of ſome exerciſe of Religion.</hi> 5thly. He muſt be <hi>preſent</hi> at ſuch Aſſembly or Meeting under ſuch colour or pretence of ſome <hi>exerciſe</hi> of Religion. 6thly. That ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion muſt be in another manner <hi>then is allowed by the Lyturgie, or Practice of the Church of</hi> England. 7thly. There muſt be <hi>preſent</hi> at this Aſſembly <hi>five perſons</hi> over and above thoſe of the ſame houſhold. If the Witneſſes fail in any one of theſe Particulars, the Indictment is <hi>void.</hi> Now Sir, I beſeech you, Where ſhall we find Witneſſes competent for ſuch Evidence? Take, for example, a Meeting of <hi>Quakers,</hi> for they are moſt <hi>free</hi> and <hi>open</hi> in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; who will be ſo daring as to venture his ſoul upon it, That they meet together <hi>under pretence or colour of any exerciſe of Religion in other manner then is allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of England?</hi> or if any ſhould be ſo bold and mad, as to make no Conſcience of Swearing any thing that the Judges ſhould bid him Swear, Shall you, or I, be ſo mad as to believe him, or be ſatisfied in our conſciences that it is ſo? For, let us conſider, what knowledge is requiſite in ſuch a Witneſs, and then try the <hi>Hackney-Witneſſes</hi> whether they be ſo qualified. Firſt, It is neceſſary, that he <hi>know every ſingle perſon</hi> againſt whom he <hi>bears</hi> Teſtimony, was there <hi>preſent</hi> under colour or pretence of Religion: But how ſhould he know this, except every ſuch perſon ſhould tell him ſo? But they do conſtantly aver, That they come not together under any pretence or colour (As pretence and colour is oppoſed to intention and reality) and therefore are not guilty. I beſeech you, mark, the <hi>Act</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be preſent at any exerciſe of Religion,</hi> but, <hi>ſhall be preſent</hi> [<hi>under pretence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62463:5"/>
of any exerciſe of Religion</hi>; which words of <hi>pretence</hi> and <hi>colour</hi> are to no purpoſe, and might have been ſpared, if to be [<hi>preſent</hi>] at a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Meeting be ſufficient to make a man guilty. So that really, according to the beſt underſtanding I have, they do wickedly abuſe the King and Parliament that adjudge men guilty upon any other ſcore. Again, It is uſual both for <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> to viſit one another, and being together, they take occaſion to do ſome Act of Religion, and perhaps, are found therein, and apprehended; What, did they therefore come together under colour of Religion, becauſe they are Religious? Are both thoſe that profeſs to meet for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and thoſe that profeſs it not, but ſomewhat elſe, equally guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Such a Witneſs muſt be of wonderful diſcerning.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe we, that our Judges will perſwade the ſilly Witneſſes, that, if they were found Praying, or Exhorting one another, that then the <hi>pretence</hi> of Religion is evident, (for I will not imagin ſo much wickedneſs in any of our Judges as in <hi>Br.</hi> to adjudge men guilty, <hi>that ſay, nor do any thing</hi>) But 2dly. our Witneſs muſt know, that this exerciſe of Religion was in other manner then is allowed by the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> or practice of the Church of <hi>England</hi>; and how ſhall he know that? Can any man tell what the <hi>Lyturgie</hi> allows, except he hath read it all, and every part, or heard it read? and truly, there is little leſs than the whole Bible contained in the <hi>Litturgy,</hi> if you conſider the <hi>Epiſtles, Goſpels</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> that are there appointed to be read. So that the reſult will be, Whether this exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be allowed in the <hi>Bible,</hi> or <hi>Lyturgy</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then it will be neceſſary that our <hi>Deponent</hi> have read or known, underſtood, and remembred all, and every part of the holy Scriptures; all, and every part of the <hi>Litturgy</hi>; all, and every part of the <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> concerning Religion, whether it be written, or not written. He muſt alſo be able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this exerciſe of Religion in the accuſed Aſſembly, with the <hi>Scriptures, Litturgy,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> He muſt alſo be able to determine all Controverſies in Religion, to know on which ſide the Truth lies between the party accuſed and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion allowed by the Scriptures, Lyturgy, or Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and if perhaps the Lyturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do thwart and contradict the Scriptures, or one another, or themſelves concerning this point of Religion in queſtion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62463:5"/>
ſo that they do in ſome places allow it, and in other places diſallow it: our Witneſs muſt be able to determine certainly upon his Oath, That this exerciſe of Religion is not allowed by the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi>; and then, <hi>eris mihi magnus Apollo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, perhaps, That it is determined by the Church of <hi>England</hi> already what only exerciſe of Religion is allowed, and by conſequence all other are diſallowed: So that, the Witneſs needs only to tell, In what manner they exerciſed Religion, and the Judges will tell the Jury, That the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth allow it, and then it will be clear between the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Judges to the Jury-man's conſcience, that the Priſoner is guilty according to the <hi>Indictment.</hi> But will this ſatisfie you Sir? Can you take a paſſionate and teaſty Judge's word as your infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Director in ſo many moſt difficult Controverſies as muſt in this caſe be decided? Will you pin your Faith upon the Judges ſleeve in matters of Religion, (of which perhaps he knows no more then he can find in the <hi>Statute-Book,</hi>) when you have rejected the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with all her pretences of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> from being Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this matter? where I pray hath the Church of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined all Acts of Religion that are to be performed by <hi>five</hi> or more perſons? Doth ſhe not tell us, the Scriptures are the Word of God? Doth ſhe not commend it as a perfect <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith, and Manners? Doth ſhe not tranſlate it into our Mother Tongue, and charge us to reade it diligiently? And muſt we not obey what we judge we find there? The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are in far better caſe than we, that are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to read the Scriptures, if when we have read them we muſt be puniſhed for underſtanding and obeying them the beſt we can. O wittily done, <hi>Robbin Everard,</hi> that didſt chooſe rather to go to <hi>Rome,</hi> than return to the Church of <hi>England!</hi> perhaps thou thought'ſt ſhe was haſtning thither, and thou wouldſt go before to get a good quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as fearing thou ſhouldſt ſcarce get any entertainment when ſo great an Army came. But to return, Doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow only one manner of exerciſe of Religion, that is, reading the <hi>Lyturgy?</hi> Why then do ye Preachers uſually make Prayers before and after your Sermons, that are not in the <hi>Lyturgy?</hi> Doth not the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow what the Scriptures command? but the divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> commands Chriſtians, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24, 25. <hi>To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider one another, to provoke one another to Love, and to Good Works, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62463:6"/>
not to forſake the aſſembling themſelves together, as the manner of ſome is</hi>: For how ſhould they provoke one another to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Good-Works,</hi> if they ſhould not Aſſemble? but you will ſay, They muſt aſſemble among their Neighbors at Church; but there is only one permitted to exhort the reſt, if any other ſhould ſpeak there to exhort one another, he ſhould preſently be haled to priſon, and perhaps loſe his life among the Rabble. The ſame Author commands us <hi>to exhort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daily, while it is called to day, leſt any be hardened through the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of ſin.</hi> What, wil not the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow us to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prevent the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and hadneſs of heart? Surely the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> (in the Letany) hath one clauſe againſt hardneſs of heart; muſt we pray againſt it, and not labour againſt it? How ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd is that? Or what? doth not the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow a man to reade the Scriptures or the Lyturgy in his own Family, if there be five perſons beſides his Family? And is not reading the Scriptures an exerciſe of Religion? Doth not the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow <hi>five</hi> perſons beſides the Family to meet together, to conſult of relieving <hi>a poor Widow or Fatherleſs,</hi> and to exhort and ſtir up one another to this work by mutual Conference or continued Speeches, and Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the Scriptures, and to pray for one another, that they <hi>may keep themſelves unſpotted</hi> from the Adulteries, Fornications, Prophane Swearings, Oppreſſions, Cruelties, Malice, Envie, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Covenant-Breaking, Perſecution of Good men, and all manner of Debaucherys of the times? But the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pure Religion, and undefiled is this, to viſit the Fatherleſs and Widdows in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the world.</hi> Who will dare to take his Oath, the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not this allow? Again, I would fain know whether a man may not invite <hi>ſix</hi> poor People to his Houſe, and there feed their hungry bodies, and inſtruct their ignorant ſouls in the knowledge of the Goſpel, without incurring the penalty of this Law? Is not this an Act of <hi>Religion?</hi> Can any man be ſaved without <hi>Charity?</hi> Doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us to go in the way to Heaven, except it baniſh us to <hi>Barbados</hi> or <hi>Jamaico?</hi> It ſhall be lawful there to obey God and be Merciful, but not in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> bids us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and mourn with them that mourn</hi>; and the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> bids us <hi>Confeſs our faults one to another, and pray one for another,</hi> (Jam. 5.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62463:6"/>
16.) that we may be healed; What, muſt we not do it, five or ſix together, without Baniſhment? Doth not the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow it? Have we not juſt cauſe to ſay to theſe, as our Lord ſaid to the Scribes and Phariſes, <hi>Thus have ye made the Commandment of God of none effect by your Tradition,</hi> Statute.</p>
            <p>Nay, beſides the Contradiction to our Saviour's Commands, Doth not ſuch an Interpretation of this Law, (forbidding all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of ſix perſons, but what is performed at Church by hearing a Parſon, reade the Lyturgy, as the never-to-be-forgotten Judge <hi>Bridgman</hi> expounded it to the ever-to-be-remarked <hi>Hartford</hi> Juryes) Doth it not I ſay, make us inhumane beaſts, as well as irreligious men and women? for how can a man in prudence ſuffer his wife to go to her neighbours labour when ſhe cryes out for her help, leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there ſhould be four more, and they all be taken for Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers, for certainly in ſuch extremities, it is uſual for the Labouring woman to cry to God for help, which is a plain Act of Religion; nay, I hear it is common to the good Women after they have finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their work, for the Midwife or ſome other to give thanks, and pray ſolemnly in other manner than is any where to be found in the Lyturgy. Let it therefore be conſidered, that the Travelling-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or any other for her, be henceforth prohibited to pray unto God in ſuch caſes, leſt ſhe bring upon her Neighbours for their good-will and humanity, the penalty of three or ſix months impriſonment, or Baniſhment for ſeven years. Or for better ſecurity, let the Parſon alwayes be ſent for as ſoon as the Midwife, to act his part among the good women till their work be finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Again, how will it be ſafe for a man to go to his deceaſed Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours funeral, leſt ſome body ſhould ſalute the ſurviving Relative with a <hi>I pray God comfort you,</hi> or I pray <hi>God give you Joy after your Sorrow,</hi> and ſo make the whole company liable to a penalty? The like may be ſaid, for praying <hi>Joy</hi> to a new married Couple, or ſaying <hi>God be with you</hi> to our friend, taking a Journey by Land, or a Voyage by Sea, or much more for five perſons going to their neighbours to dinner, except the Prieſt be there to ſay <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laſtly, I know not how any perſons meeting together upon any Occaſion whatſoever can eſcape, taking Judge <hi>Bridgman</hi>'s Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for Law, that is, ſaith he, <hi>You muſt not expect a plain punctual Evidence againſt them for any thing they ſaid or did at their Meeting,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62463:7"/>
for they may speak to one another, though not with or by auriculer ſound, but by a caſt of the eye, or a motion of the head or foot, or geſture of the body, &amp;c. if you find or believe in your hearts that they were in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under colour of Religion in their way, though they ſate ſtill only, and looked upon each other, ſeeing they cannot ſay what they did there, it was an Unlawful Meeting, &amp;c.</hi> If they are ſworn to give Verdict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Evidence, may proceed to condemn men without Evidence according to what they believe in their heart; and if they may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing or ſeeing what they did, judge them according to what <hi>may be</hi> in their hearts or geſtures; then may the Judge have his skin pulled over his ears for falſe Judgment, for <hi>it may be</hi> he knows in his own conſcience it was ſo. But ſaith he, <hi>their uſe and practice was not according to the Lyturgie of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>for it allows and commands when people meet together in the Church, that Divine Service ſhould be read, &amp;c.</hi> Is it not rarely well argued? the Lyturgy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that when people meet together in the Church, Divine Service ſhall be read, therefore it doth not allow that when people are met together in a private houſe, Divine Exhortations ſhould be given, or that people ſhould ſit together without ſaying or doing any thing. This is not <hi>Lawyers Latin,</hi> but <hi>Lawyers Logick,</hi> and the great and dreadful God of Heaven and Earth will try it, whether it be made in any true mode or figure of Juſtice. I have proved to you that in many caſes, and might in many more, that if the Lyturgy be not contrary to the Scriptures and it ſelf, it allows of Meetings and Acts of Religion, the manner whereof is not determined by the Lyturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> The Judge might as well have argued thus; The Lyturgy allows men to eat and drink Bread and Wine given by the hand of a Prieſt at Church; Therefore men may not eat and drink Bread and Wine with thankſgiving at their own Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. If a Sophiſter in the Schools ſhould uſe ſuch a Fallacy, he might be hiſſed at for a <hi>Dunce,</hi> and there's an end on't; but to delude God and Jury-mens Conſciences, and to baniſh harmleſs and meek men from their Native Country, Husbands from their dear Wives, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents from their tender Babes, Kinsfolk from Kinsfolk, and loving Neighbours and Friends from the ſweet ſociety of their Neighbours and Friends; this is intolerable, and a Judgment that God will judge! and I perſwade my ſelf you will ever keep your ſelf from partaking in ſuch groſs Iniquity. And this leads me to the conſideration the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62463:7"/>
Equitableneſs of the puniſhment, and the proportion that is between that and the Offence; for in all juſt Laws the penalty is not greater than the nature of the Fault requires. Now ſuppoſing the Fault to be ſuch as the Interpreters would make us believe, that is, that men and women from an erroneous perſwaſion do meet together to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in other manner than is allowed by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> can it be imagined the Parliament would puniſh ſuch an Error as this with horrid <hi>Baniſhment for ſeven years?</hi> far be it from us to think ſo unworthily of an <hi>Engliſh Parliament.</hi> No, the Intention of the Parliament is manifeſt from the Title and Preface of the Act: the Title, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs ſeditious Conventicles:</hi> but what Sedition in worſhipping God erroneouſly? The Preface, <hi>For remedy againſt Seditious Sectaries and other diſloyal perſons, who under pretence of Tender Conſciences, do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore the matter of Fact is, perſons meeting under <hi>colour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion</hi>; whereby it plainly appears they intended not to puniſh thoſe that have no other Intention in their religious Exerciſes but what appears; but ſuch as only pretend Religion for Seditious ends: To ſuch indeed, where that Seditious mind is diſcovered and manifeſt, the puniſhment may be proportionate; but for perſons that have no other intention in Meeting, or at leaſt in whom no other intention can any way be made manifeſt, but to pleaſe God and ſatisfie their own Conſciences, for them to be puniſhed in this manner, is like as if a Parent ſhould baniſh one of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren out of his preſence, and from his table, into <hi>Jamaica</hi> or <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos</hi> to be educated among his <hi>Cow-herds</hi> and <hi>Hog-herds</hi> for ſeven years, becauſe he hath a weak ſtomach and cannot eat the wholſome food of the other Children. Therefore it is wholly to be held that either this is not the puniſhment, or that is not the offence; for there is no proportion between them.</p>
            <p>Again, how can it be imagined the <hi>Parliament</hi> would forbid all religious Meetings, ſave at the Pariſh Church, becauſe thirty men once came out of ſuch a Meeting to make a Sedition and Tumult? Can any man ſuppoſe that Inſurrections are contrived in a Meeting of eighty or an hundred People of all ſorts, Men, Women and Children? Surely no State or Kingdom need fear ſuch Plots; Are not Inſurrections rather contrived in ſecret chambers, where queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there are not above five beſides thoſe of the houſhold? why
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62463:8"/>
ſhould it not therefore be prohibited for men to come together upon any occaſion whatſoever in any number? You will ſay this cannot be, for it will deſtroy Trading and Society? But what I pray, is not trading for Heaven and religious Society, as neceſſary as civil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and wordly Commodities? But you will ſay, They may meet at the Pariſh Church for Religious Society: But I have ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that many things are to be done in Religion which cannot be done there, neither is it permitted if it could. And beſides Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath been moved and acted at the publick Church, witneſs <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the beginning of the late Wars; and <hi>Dr. Duck</hi> at <hi>Magnes</hi>: A common thing to preach Sedition in the Pulpit. Muſt we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be prohibited from meeting at Church, and commanded to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God at home, every Family by it ſelf? if ſome perſons abuſe of a thing could have made it unlawful, we ſhould by this time have had nothing lawful. The preaching of the Goſpel was in the pureſt times, done by ſome out of envy, and yet that did not hinder o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from doing it out of good will. The Grace of God was by ſome turned into Laſciviouſneſs, yet it taught others to deny all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly luſts, &amp;c. Thoſe that met Seditiouſly, were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as offenſive to thoſe that meet now peaceably, and religiouſly, as they were to the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, upon the whole matter, that I may draw to a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Can you believe in your conſcience that the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>others</hi> that come before you for religious Meetings, have ſeditious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and Contrivances under the pretence of Religion? Do you think it poſſible for any Witneſs or Judge on Earth to ſatisfie your ſworn conſcience, that the Exerciſe of Religion among the <hi>Quakers</hi> or any other profeſſion among us is not allowed by the Scriptures, Lyturgy or Practice of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Miſtake me not, I ſay not that you cannot be ſatisfied in conſcience that ſome profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions do err in ſome matters of Doctrine or Practice, ſo as that you can neither conſent with them, nor do as they do: But can you take your Oath that they err <hi>maliciouſly?</hi> Can you venture your Eternal Salvation on it, that their exerciſe of Religion is a ſin that deſerves to be puniſhed with ſeven years Baniſhment?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the Witneſs ſay, they were met together at a private houſe, and prayed together, and exhorted one another, but did not reade either their Prayers or Exhortations out of a Book called the <hi>Lyturgy,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62463:8"/>
and the Judge tell you that this is ſufficient as to matter of fact; can you hereupon pawn your Soul and all your earthly comforts, that they are guilty according to the Indictment? They ſhall be baniſhed out of their Country for ſeven years; Will you freely be baniſhed out of Heaven evermore, if they be not ſufficiently proved guilty? They ſhall be ſent to <hi>Jamaico</hi> or <hi>Barbados</hi>; Will you be ſent to Hell if they be not ſufficiently proved guilty? They ſhall be ſeparated from their Wives, Children, Parents, Kinsfolk, Friends and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for ſeven years; will you willingly be ſeparated from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord and his holy Angels and Saints for ever, if they be not ſufficiently proved guilty? They ſhall be damnified in their Trades, and in the comfortable enjoyment of their Families and Friends; are you willing to be curſed by God in your Trades, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, Friends, and in whatſoever is dear to you, if they be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proved guilty? They ſhall be hanged up as Felons if they return without Licence in ſeven years ſpace; can you appeal to God with a good conſcience, and ſay before the great and dreadful Judge of Heaven and Earth; Lord, let me ſuffer Death and Damnation as a Murderer, if theſe perſons be not ſufficiently proved guilty? Whoever underſtands the nature of an Oath and Verdict, this is the Caſe between the Jury-man and the Priſoner.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, Perhaps the Judge will be angry, &amp; threaten, and ſay, <hi>My Maſters, will you make a noſe of wax of the Law, and ſuffer the Law to be baffled? thoſe that think to deceive the Law, the Law will deceive them</hi>: and perhaps I ſhall be ſent for to the Court and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> and ſo be undone by great Charges and loſs of my Trade. But ſuch a thing as that would be ſuch Injuſtice as never was heard of; and it cannot be imagined, that his Majeſty would ſuffer it: It is altogether improbable that any man ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this kind: I only ſuppoſe the worſt that can be ſuppoſed; and if the worſt is to be endured; how much more when it ſhall be only a chiding? I ask thee again, Whether thou hadſt rather incur the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God or of man? Whether thou hadſt rather ſuffer from men in thy Trade, Family and Liberty, or be curſed by God in them all? Whether the <hi>Gatehouſe or Hell</hi> be worſe? Whether it be not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to truſt God, with a good conſcience, than to truſt the Devil with a bad one? If thou doſt believe that God rules the world, that he favoureth and bleſſeth the Righteous, and puniſheth the Wicked,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62463:9"/>
both in this world, and that which is to come, then keep thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence clean, doe righteouſly though thou ſuffer by it: <hi>Fear not them that kill the body, and have no more that they can do; But rather fear him, which is able to deſtroy both body and ſoul in Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why do I uſe ſuch ſevere expoſtulations with you, of whoſe tenderneſs of conſcience I have ſo great and clear evidence? I know you can ſooner dye upon the place, then bring in any ſuch peaceable perſon, <hi>Guilty</hi>; as well knowing that there is a heavy <hi>Wo</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt him that ſhall <hi>offend the leaſt of Chriſt's little ones; it were better for him that a Milſtone were hanged about his neck, and he caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depth of the Sea.</hi> I know you do approve of that moſt prudent counſel of that moſt Famous Doctor of Law amongſt the <hi>Jews, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel</hi>; Act. 5.38, 39. <hi>Refrain from theſe men, and let them alone, (for if this Counſelor this Work be of men it will come to nought, but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it) leſt happily ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi> I cannot but much wonder, with what conſcience two Juſtices of Peace, or one Cheif Magiſtrate, can play the parts of <hi>Judge, Jury,</hi> and <hi>Witneſs,</hi> againſt theſe poor men, and condemn them for <hi>Meetting Seditiouſly,</hi> becauſe they meet ſimply to exerciſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion according to their conſcience. I appeal to you, whether this Oppreſſion doth not call for the Judgments of God upon the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord give them that are guilty in this kind, Repentance and Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins; and deliver you from partaking with them, either in their Sin or Puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Your affectionate Chriſtian Friend <hi>H. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
